<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: analytics | Himanshu Gilani]]></title>
  <link href="http://hgilani.github.com/blog/categories/analytics/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hgilani.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-03-05T10:03:06+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://hgilani.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Himanshu Gilani]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Scripting Google Analytics: Part 2 - Logging, Custom Variables & Traffic Sources]]></title>
    <link href="http://hgilani.github.com/blog/2013/03/03/scripting-google-analytics-part-2-logging-custom-variables-and-tracking-traffic-sources/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-03T21:19:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://hgilani.github.com/blog/2013/03/03/scripting-google-analytics-part-2-logging-custom-variables-and-tracking-traffic-sources</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In <a href="http://himanshu.gilani.info/blog/2013/01/16/scripting-google-analytics-part-1-tracking-pages-and-events/">part 1</a> of this post I explained how to track page views and events in <a href="http://www.google.com/analytics/">Google Analytics</a>. In this post I will explain</p>

<ul>
<li>How to use Google Analytics for logging data and javascript errors.</li>
<li>Custom Variables in Google Analytics.
*How to use Google Analytics for track traffic sources.</li>
</ul>


<!-- more -->


<h2>Logging data and Javascript Errors</h2>

<p>Google Analytics events could be used for logging custom data and tracking Javascript errors in Google Analytics. For logging data just execute following</p>

<p><code>javascript Logging Data
_gaq.push(['_trackEvent', 'INFO', 'Data to log...', url]);  
</code></p>

<p>This mechanism could also be used to track error codes or messages received from AJAX calls or a REST service call. Following example assumes <code>response.code</code> contains the error code received in an AJAX call.</p>

<p><code>javascript Logging Error Codes
_gaq.push(['_trackEvent', 'ERROR', response.code, url]);  
</code></p>

<p>We could also use the same approach for tracking global javascript errors that are not handled.</p>

<p>``` javascript Tracking Javascript errors using Google Analytics
window.onerror = function(message, file, lineNumber) {</p>

<pre><code>_gaq.push(['_trackEvent', 'Error', file + ':' + lineNumber, message + '']);
</code></pre>

<p>};
```</p>

<p>This snippet simply attaches a callback on the <code>onerror</code> callback of the <code>window</code> object for logging errors.</p>

<h2>Custom Variables</h2>

<p>Google Analytics is pretty good in tracking page views, but a lot of times we need a way to attach custom data to the page views. Custom variables in Google Analytics lets you do this. For setting a custom variable you could add following snippet</p>

<p><code>ruby Setting Up Custom Variables
_gaq._setCustomVar(index, name, value, scope)
</code></p>

<p>In the above snippet, <code>_setCustomVar</code> has 4 arguments.</p>

<ul>
<li><code>index</code> argument is a slot or the position of the variable. Google Analytics only allows you track 5 variables per page page view and as a result this argument has a value between 1 to 5.</li>
<li><code>name</code> and <code>value</code> define the data that you are tracking. Think of it as <strong>key - value</strong> data associated with the current page view.</li>
<li><p><code>scope</code> argument defines the duration for which Google Analytics should track this variable. It can take a value between 1 to 3 i.e. 1 (page level), 2 (session level) and 3 (visitor level)</p>

<ol>
<li><strong>Page</strong> level scope means variable would be tracked only for the duration of current page view.</li>
<li><strong>Session</strong> level means variable applies to a single session or visit.</li>
<li><strong>Visitor</strong> level means variable would be tracked across sessions till users removes the Analytics cookie.</li>
</ol>
</li>
</ul>


<h3>Custom Variables gotchas</h3>

<ol>
<li>You can only set 5 variables per page view.</li>
<li>Do not change the variable names and slots (index) across page views. This will help in keeping things consistent.</li>
<li>Custom variable are tied to the current page view. So, any variable that you want to be tracked with the page view should be set before the <code>_trackPageview</code> call.</li>
</ol>


<h3>Custom Variables uses</h3>

<p>You might wonder what can I do with custom variables, well possibilities are endless. Once you start tracking some custom information then you could go in Google Analytics and do some custom analysis to understand how users behave with your website. Following are some examples of what to track using custom variables</p>

<ol>
<li>Identify type of user  who viewed the page e.g. visitor, member, gold-user, platinum-user, etc</li>
<li>Track demographic information e.g. age, gender, etc of users who viewed the page.</li>
<li>Track how user arrived at the page e.g. paid search campaign, RSS, email newsletter, social n/w, etc</li>
<li>Track users who successfully shopped on your website.</li>
<li>Track users who contacted customer support.</li>
</ol>


<h2>Track Traffic Sources</h2>

<p>When the visitors start coming to your website then one of the metrics that you would want to track is who is referring users to your website. Users might have discovered your website through a search engine like Google, Yahoo, Bing, etc or might have come to your website by following a link from the newsletter you sent. But, if you want to track other sources then you need to format your inbound URL with following attributes</p>

<ul>
<li><code>utm_source</code>: name of the traffic source e.g. bing.com, email newsletter, social, etc</li>
<li><code>utm_medium</code>: medium through which user came to your website e.g. cpc campaign, email, RSS, etc</li>
<li><code>utm_campaign</code>: string that lets you identify you campaigns e.g. bing_campaign_1, Spring 2013 newsletter, etc</li>
<li><code>utm_term</code>: keywords or tags that you want to associate with the source in Google Analytics</li>
</ul>


<p>Using these attributes an inbound URL in email newsletter would be formatted like</p>

<p><code>
http://mementodb.com?utm_source=email_newsletter&amp;utm_medium=email&amp;utm_campaign=spring_newsletter
</code></p>

<p>Google Analytics automatically tracks the traffic sources, keywords, and type of search i.e. organic or paid (Ad Words campaign) for all traffic coming from google.com What this means is that if you are using an Ad Words campaign then you don't need to do anything. But for traffic coming from Bing Ads it will not track the keywords and campaign details. Luckily this could be easily fixed but you would need to format the destination URL of the ads in Bing Ads account to use the <code>utm_source</code>, <code>utm_medium</code>, <code>utm_campaign</code>, and <code>utm_term</code> query parameters. If the bing campaign name is campaign_1 then this URL would be formatted as shown below</p>

<p><code>
http://mementodb.com?utm_source=bing&amp;utm_medium=cpc&amp;utm_campaign=campaign_1&amp;utm_term={QueryString}
</code></p>

<p>In this URL pay attention to <strong>{QueryString}</strong> this should be entered exactly as shown with curly braces as Bind Ads platform will dynamically replace with search terms when the ad is served.</p>

<p>Follow me on twitter <a href="http://twitter.com/hgilani">here</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Scripting Google Analytics: Part 1 - Tracking Pages and Events]]></title>
    <link href="http://hgilani.github.com/blog/2013/01/16/scripting-google-analytics-part-1-tracking-pages-and-events/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-16T11:31:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://hgilani.github.com/blog/2013/01/16/scripting-google-analytics-part-1-tracking-pages-and-events</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.google.com/analytics">Google Analytics</a> is a free web analytics tool from Google that you can use for tracking website statistics like page views, traffic sources, audience information, goals, funnels, etc. While a lot of the stuff is tracked automatically, it becomes overwhelming pretty quickly if you want to track customize analytics or want to track or create custom metrics. In this post, I will detail things I learned by experimenting with Google Analytics.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Setup Google Analytics</h2>

<p>If you are new to Google Analytics then head over to the <a href="http://www.google.com/analytics">Google Analytics</a> website and create an account. Once you have created an account, you will be assigned a tracking code which will look like <code>UA-XXXXX-X</code>. For starting to capture analytics replace <code>UA-XXXXX-X</code> with the actual tracking code in the following code snippet and place it before the closing <code>&lt;/head&gt;</code> element of the page where you want to track analytics. Ideally you want this code to execute on every page served on your web site.</p>

<p>``` ruby Getting Started with Google Analytics</p>

<script type="text/javascript">

  var _gaq = _gaq || [];
  _gaq.push(['_setAccount', 'UA-XXXXX-X']);
  _gaq.push(['_trackPageview']);

  (function() {
    var ga = document.createElement('script'); ga.type = 'text/javascript'; ga.async = true;
    ga.src = ('https:' == document.location.protocol ? 'https://ssl' : 'http://www') + '.google-analytics.com/ga.js';
    var s = document.getElementsByTagName('script')[0]; s.parentNode.insertBefore(ga, s);
  })();

</script>


<p>```</p>

<p>The first line in this snippet initializes a JavaScript array variable <code>_gaq</code> on the page loads. You can think of this variable as a queue where you push events that you want to log in Google Analytics. In the next two lines we push two events to the tracking queue, first event(<code>_setAccount</code>) identifies the analytics account of your website and the second event(<code>_trackPageview</code>) tracks that page view i.e. some user visited the URL of the current web page. Rest of the lines dynamically add a <code>&lt;script&gt;</code> element to the web page for loading the Google Analytics library.</p>

<p>So with this in place, every time a page is loaded in the browser a <code>_trackPageview</code> event will be recorded. Along with the page tracking Google analytics automatically tracks statistics on audience language and location, type of browsers and OS used, traffic sources, visitor flow, etc</p>

<h2>Tracking page views in AJAX or Single Page Websites</h2>

<p>For the page driven websites where actions or clicks results in loading of new pages, Google Analytics will track the page views without configuring anything else. But this tracking does not work for the single page applications or AJAX enabled websites where first request to the server results in loading of the application and actions or clicks result in AJAX calls to fetch data from the server. It does not work because we only downloaded one page from the server and sent only one <code>_trackPageview</code> event. So in an AJAX application each AJAX request that updates the application view should be tracked as page view. This means we have to push the tracking event to the queue manually on each AJAX requests. Use following snippet for this</p>

<p><code>ruby Tracking page views for AJAX applications
_gaq.push(['_trackPageview', '{AJAX_REQUEST_LABEL}']);
</code></p>

<p>In this snippet {AJAX_REQUEST_LABEL} is a string that you use to identify the request. If you are using a URL router like sammy.js that changes the hash of the page URL to reflect the current route then you can use following snippet for each route</p>

<p><code>ruby tracking page hash for sammy.js style URL routers
_gaq.push(['_trackPageview', window.location.hash]);
</code></p>

<h2>Track Events</h2>

<p>Besides tracking page views, you could also track events in Google Analytics. Events are a way to record user interaction and behavior on the page such as which signUp button was clicked on the landing page or which outbound link was clicked, if the user played the video or how far user scrolled down on the web page or did user started filling the credit card form and abandoned it half way. Possibilities are endless as it opens up a way to capture metrics that could allow you to optimize or redesign the pages.</p>

<p>Events can be tracked by simply pushing <code>_trackEvent</code> message to the analytics queue. <code>_trackEvent</code> has five properties associated with it as explained in the <a href="https://developers.google.com/analytics/devguides/collection/gajs/eventTrackerGuide">Google Analytics Developer Guide</a></p>

<ol>
<li>Category (required): The name you supply for the group of objects you want to track.</li>
<li>Action (required): A string that is uniquely paired with each category, and commonly used to define the type of user interaction for the web object.</li>
<li>Label (optional): An optional string to provide additional dimensions to the event data.</li>
<li>value (optional): An integer that you can use to provide numerical data about the user event.</li>
<li>non-interaction (optional): A boolean that when set to true, indicates that the event hit will not be used in bounce-rate calculation.</li>
</ol>


<p>To track an even simply push <code>_trackEvent</code> message to the analytics queue.</p>

<p><code>ruby Tracking Events in Google Analytics
_gaq.push(['_trackEvent', 'category', 'action', 'label']);
</code></p>

<p>The simplest use of the <code>_trackEvent</code> is to attach it to the DOM events such as <code>onClick</code>, <code>onScroll</code>, <code>onKeyup</code>, etc</p>

<p><code>ruby Tracking DOM events
&lt;a href="http://mementodb.com" onclick="_gaq.push(['_trackEvent', 'category', 'action', 'label']);"&gt;Goto Memento&lt;/a&gt;
</code></p>

<p>This leaves an open question what should be the values of the <code>_trackEvent</code> properties. There are no specific values that you should or should not use. But to put things in perspective you could imagine category, action and labels as three dimensions of the event where category identifies the page, action identifies user activity on the page and label is anything helps you in tracking.To understand it clearly lets look at some examples</p>

<ol>
<li>Which login button user click on the landing page?</li>
</ol>


<p><code>ruby User clicked on Login button in header
_gaq.push(['_trackEvent', 'Landing-Page', 'Click', 'Login button in header']);
</code></p>

<p>or</p>

<p><code>ruby User clicked on Login button in body
_gaq.push(['_trackEvent', 'Landing-Page', 'Click', 'Login button in body']);
</code></p>

<ol>
<li>Which outbound link was clicked?</li>
</ol>


<p><code>ruby User clicked on mementodb.com link
_gaq.push(['_trackEvent', 'outbound link', 'click', 'outbound link to mementodb.com']);
</code></p>

<ol>
<li>Which video user played?</li>
</ol>


<p><code>ruby User played video with title "Linus Torvalds on Git"
_gaq.push(['_trackEvent', 'Videos', 'Play', 'Linus Torvalds on Git'])
</code></p>

<ol>
<li>Which version of software users are downloading?</li>
</ol>


<p><code>ruby User downloaded Trial version of the software
_gaq.push(['_trackEvent', 'Downloads', 'Installer', 'Trial version']);
</code></p>

<p><code>js User downloaded Pro version of the software
_gaq.push(['_trackEvent', 'Downloads', 'Installer', 'Pro version']);
</code></p>

<p>In the next part of this post I will go over how to analyze the traffic sources, track errors, monitor how far users scroll on your web page</p>

<p>Follow me on twitter <a href="http://twitter.com/hgilani">here</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
